<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Talk Some Cents</title>
    <link>http://talksomecents.com/blog/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Talk Some Cents</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://talksomecents.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Now What? Implementing the Budget Part 1: Becoming a Team</title>
      <link>http://talksomecents.com/blog/implementing-a-budget-part-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://talksomecents.com/blog/implementing-a-budget-part-one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The big question in everyone’s mind after they create a budget is what to do once everything is set and planned.  The short answer is: live by it.  The more detailed answer includes dealing with many unexpected circumstances that may arise.  In the next few blog entries, I am going to tackle some of the most common issues that may be encountered when first implementing your budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One frequent concern I’ve heard clients voice is this: how do you get one’s spouse on board with a budget?  Because you cannot create or implement a budget without your spouse’s support, this is a key issue to discuss.  Unless you work as a team, any attempts to manage money will fail and instead of decreasing tension and promoting peace, the opposite will occur.
In the beginning of my budget journey, my wife believed that it would not succeed and did not want to go along with it.  However, she knew that I had always handled finances for our family and so she allowed me to take over the entire thing, asking that I show her signs that it was working.  Having your spouse’s trust is a huge component to making a budget work, even if they are leery of its ultimate success.  I was able to show her how it was working throughout the first six months and she ultimately joined my enthusiasm for it. Many people believe a budget will confine them, so they may feel like following one will ruin their life.  Aim for small victories. If you can convince them to agree to a trial period, the two of you will have taken a huge step in the right direction.   If a spouse is reluctant to believe in a budget, it can help to offer to create the plan yourself at first, asking them to simply agree to follow it for a test period and let the results convince them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, if you can make the budget easier for the spouse, it will help them to participate.  Create the entire budget on the first day of each month and just review it with them.  Don’t make them sit through the agony of creating it if they are uninterested.  Some couples work collaboratively on their budget; others have one member creating/organizing and another following.  It does not matter what arrangement you come up with as long as it is one that both of you not only agree on, but follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be very careful that you do not play any “blame games” on your spouse in regards to the budget.  If he or she feels as if they are being attacked or as if you are blaming them for the debt that has accrued, they will grow defensive and unwilling to cooperate with a budget.   It is important to remember that debt is shared as a couple and blaming one of you for the debt that has incurred will never motivate change.
Some couples have found success with creating a rewards-based system.  For example, if you are working on getting rid of debt, it may help to allow the hesitant spouse to make a cash purchase after paying something off.   This will help them see that a budget does not confine you, only tells you where your money is going before it is spent and allows us to use it responsibly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one last option that I do not usually promote but have heard of couples using.  Some couples separate their income.  They sit down and calculate their yearly income contributions and distribute bills and expenses according to it.   For example, if you make ¾ of the entire yearly income, then you would be responsible for ¾ of the bills.  If your spouse makes ¼ of the yearly income, they are responsible to pay for ¼ of the bills.  At this point, then you create and implement a budget of your own with your share of the income/expenses.  This would allow you to show your spouse that it is easy to budget and that it works.  I generally frown upon this idea as I believe couples should work together on their finances, but it is better than not having any kind of financial structure or budget at all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Motivation</title>
      <link>http://talksomecents.com/blog/why-i-do-what-i-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://talksomecents.com/blog/why-i-do-what-i-do/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why am I writing this blog?  Why did I choose to become a financial advisor?  Why do I encourage people to take control of their finances every day?  I can remember the hopelessness that my wife and I felt when we lived paycheck to paycheck.  I can remember being in such tight straights that we could not even feed our children unless we charged it to our credit cards.  When I began to study and read on how to control money, it was a challenge.  We didn’t see eye to eye at first and many times after.  We had to make painful adjustments and implement changes that were very uncomfortable for us.  But once we began our budget journey and started to put into practice what we had planned, we found a new way of life that gave us hope.  Our stress and resentment left.  I realized that there was great joy and contentment involved with understanding how to manage money and budget and that I could pass these on to anyone.  It makes me happy to help other people achieve peace and joy regarding their finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a well known fact that finances are one of the most common sources of conflict in marriages today.  My wife and I no longer fight about money because we are now on the same page and participating in the same plan.  We know that we will have a great retirement and that we will no longer have to live paycheck to paycheck.  It relieved stress and made life together much easier for us.  If I can help other couples achieve this as well, I am confident that life can be breathed into their families again.  Until they do it themselves, people will never understand how living within their paycheck and understanding money brings freedom.  This is the reason I became a financial advisor: to pass this peace and independence onto as many people as I possibly can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will never see a multi-million dollar company without a financial plan.  Their income is high and they make a plan every year.  They even hire a person whose sole purpose is to do this for them.  But did you know that in our lifetime, we can make over $3,000,000 and have absolutely no plan ? As a financial advisor, I help people create a plan and budget for their life.  Without a plan, no one will succeed and without goals no one will get where they are going. I hold my clients accountable to the plan that we have laid out so that in 30 years, they can live a life of their choosing during retirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of real-life budget success achievements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One married couple paid off $20,000 in student loans within two years of working their budget and financial plan.  They are now completely debt free and saving for their first home while planning yearly vacations and contributing to a retirement fund.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One family behind on all household bills started a budget and began using You Need a Budget.  Within a year, they had enough in their bank account to cover expenses a month in advance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another couple managed to pay off $6,000 in credit card debt within three months, enabling them to make better use of those monthly payments towards things they really needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One woman was going further in debt each month; after one month of paying attention and following a budget, she was able to make a payment of $800 to her credit card.  Within three months, her credit cards were paid off and she was able to start planning for a house purchase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are not impossible pipe dreams!  These people came from different backgrounds, financial situations, and lifestyles.  They have different family sizes, different expenses and different goals. But they all have two things in common: a budget and a desire to change their lives.  That is all that matters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Review of Budget Apps</title>
      <link>http://talksomecents.com/blog/a-review-of-budget-apps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://talksomecents.com/blog/a-review-of-budget-apps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have learned that if you begin a budget and allow it to build, within six to nine months it will be possible to have enough “excess” money for an entire month’s worth of bills.  This is when the budget begins to be fun!  At that point, it becomes possible to budget an entire month and use the money you are making for next month’s bills – allowing you to never fall behind again.  This is the ultimate goal of a working budget.  I have used many different budget apps in order to fully embrace this kind of lifestyle.   I am always researching ways to make a budget easier in order to improve my money habits.  The three budget websites I have used and will talk about are: You Need a Budget (YNAB.com), Calendar Budget (calendarbudget.com), and a brand new one called Proactive (proactivebudget.com).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one that I use the most is YNAB.  It is user friendly and has changed my budget lifestyle. It is a glorified checking account.  The set up process is very simple.  Initially, you will create categories and allot money to each category according to the amount in your checking account and guided by monthly expenses and savings.   It is important to plot out where your dollars are going and create a coordinating category.  YNAB holds you accountable because it allows you to check each category for available funds prior to spending.  It also presents a detailed picture of where the funds lie so that instead of thinking that you have “X” amount of money in your checking account to spend, you will know exactly how much of that total amount is “free” and how much is fixed for specific costs or needs.   YNAB also allows for users to have non-expenditure categories for regular updates on your savings goals.   YNAB employs both a computer-based program and a smart phone app.  It allows you to access and manipulate your budget from either, and syncs flawlessly between multiple household phones.   YNAB charges $5 a month for the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: $5 per month
Pros: user friendly; can sync between multiple phones
Cons: must have a desktop to access all features&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calendar Budget is a free website that uses a different style to keep track of bills and expenditures.  It is formatted on a calendar, and allows you to see the dates that each bill is due, as well as salary pay dates.  After inputting expenditures and income, it allows you to look ahead in the year and see the end result of staying with the budget and how much money will be accrued.   Personally, I do not use this site very often.  There is no cost involved with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: Free
Pros: FREE, FREE, FREE!  Provides ability to see bills on a calendar format&lt;br /&gt;
Cons: less user friendly; requires a learning curve to get used to how it works&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newest site I have reviewed is Proactive Budget.  With this service, you are given a credit card.  This card can be “loaded” with money.  It also employs an app that allows categories (similar to YNAB).   When using this system, the card will be declined when used unless you allocate which category the money should come from.  This forces you to think before spending and eliminates overspending.  I personally have not used this app, but I like the principles that it uses.  It seems like a great choice.   This one costs more than the others, but the savings gained from using it would easily cover the cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost: $5.75 per month for the budget app.  $29 per year for the companion card.
Pros:  Excellent concept; requires you to have the money in order to spend it; helps keep you disciplined
Cons: Can be slightly time consuming to fill the pre-paid card each month&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of which budget app or website or combination approach you use, you will save money the moment you begin to implement a plan.  I have used multiple programs and switched many times to gain more experience and knowledge of money management.  These three are the most straightforward and user friendly ones I have encountered.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Budget Story Continues: You Will Always Fail at Money Without a Plan</title>
      <link>http://talksomecents.com/blog/my-budget-story-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://talksomecents.com/blog/my-budget-story-continues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It isn’t how much money you make that matters but rather the plan that you make with that money. My family and I have used many different products to budget.  We have done a budget on paper. We have used phone applications.  We have used websites.   The only criterion for choosing the best tool for your budget is to ensure that it works for you and your family and that you will use it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the number one goal in budgeting is to make sure every dollar has a job to do, an effective tool is one that allows you to see everything in action in order to achieve the equation, “Income – Expense =$0.” Otherwise, you are doing the budget incorrectly.   If using a pencil and paper makes this achievable for you, or if you work best with a fancier Excel spreadsheet, or even if you want to find a software program or phone app, it really does not matter.   Just ensure that you are working on your budget in some manner at least once a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In future blogs, I will review several of the most popular budgeting tools that are available and evaluate their effectiveness and ease of use.   But in this segment of my own personal budget story, I will just state that my favorite out of all of these options is the program, You Need a Budget (YNAB).  I call it my glorified checking account. It is very easy to use. The thing I like about it is that it keeps you very organized and you cannot overspend if you are implementing the strategy correctly.  YNAB consists of various categories, both income and expenditure related, and is accessible on both a computer and individual smart phones.   Once you enter the values into each budget category, you can see at a glance exactly where your money is and where it needs to go.  By updating the budget regularly (even immediately after a purchase, when using the smart phone app), it is possible to know the exact amount that remains in each category.    For example, instead of thinking that you have $5,000 in your checking account and spending without foresight, by using YNAB, you can look at your categories on the computer or phone and realize that there is only $200 in the Eating Out category, or $450 in the Groceries category.  This allows you to spend within your budget, limits overspending, and keeps you in control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within six to nine months of following the YNAB budget, I was a month ahead on my bills.  This was amazing, considering that during the first eight years of my marriage, I had been living paycheck to paycheck.  YNAB helped me to form significant money habits that I continue to this day.  Each month, I spend 10 minutes with my budget, accessing the YNAB app and creating categories and expenses for next four weeks.   In the beginning, I failed miserable at this. I overspent and I forgot categories. But the one thing that kept me going was the knowledge that if I was overspending WITH a budget, I would have been spending twice that amount WITHOUT one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Budget Story Continued</title>
      <link>http://talksomecents.com/blog/my-budget-story-continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://talksomecents.com/blog/my-budget-story-continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My family and I had to make many sacrifices as we worked to get out of debt.  The first thing we had to do was to “stop the bleeding.” We cut up all credits cards and refused to create new debt.   We had also gotten into a habit of “robbing Peter to pay Paul.”  For example, we would borrow money from my brother in order to pay off credit cards, but within 12 months, the card would be at maximum again.  No one can borrow their way out of debt.  There needed to be a definite plan.  No matter how much money we made, without a plan, we would continue to live paycheck to paycheck, indefinitely.   We were spending more than our income in pursuit of what we thought was the American Dream.  Soon, we realized that you can put yourself into debt overnight, but it takes years to get out of it. Without a budget, we would never be in control of our money and we would continue to spend more than we made.   A little time and effort went a long way towards putting us in control and eliminating stress from our lives and marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create our budget, we began by estimating and then tracking and confirming costs.  These included things like bills, utilities, groceries, eating out and any other extra costs (such as birthdays, potential vacations, holidays, etc.)  We also wrote down all of our debts, listing them from smallest to largest to get an idea of what needed to be tackled.  We started by deciding to pay towards the smallest debt first, so that we would gain a simpler “win” and feel empowered to continue the journey.  After that, we began each month by figuring out how much money we would have for the entire month.  We subtracted all of the before-mentioned costs.  The goal is for the mathematics of this to add up to a big, fat zero.   It most certainly did not do so in the beginning.   Modifications to the budget were made as we became more conscientious of our spending and as we began tracking income and expenditures more carefully.   The most important principle in budgeting is to give every dollar a “job.”  Make sure every dollar has a place to go, and pair your income with your budget in order to know exactly where it is going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One very important part of budgeting is saving.  Always remember to pay yourself first.  We knew that if we ever wanted to achieve financial freedom, we had to make sure that we put money into our savings account first.   So many times, people say, “If I make more money, then I’ll save.”  Or, “I can’t afford to save!”  In reality, it’s about saying (over and over again): you can’t afford NOT to save.  When a person decides to run a marathon, they do not begin with the entire race.  They begin with training in small amounts and distances.  In budgeting and working towards being debt free, you must begin with baby steps.  You must train yourself to build the self control involved with saving.  A small start is all that is needed.  We began with a very small amount and built it up over time, as the debt decreased and we had more flexibility.  By the time finances allowed for larger amounts to be set aside, we had already created and maintained the habit and were able to benefit from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all these principles were mapped out and initiated, we then began looking at ways in which the budget would allow for extra money to be applied towards our debt, beyond the minimum payments.  As part of this step, we changed some things about our lives.  We moved out of our home and into a 400-square foot trailer to reduce daily living costs.  We began to plan out our meals to reduce grocery expenses.  We did many other things to help financially that will be the subject of another blog post, but the key point is that our budget and some lifestyle changes made it possible to start immediately on the ultimate goal of eliminating debt.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Budget Story: It&#39;s not what you make; it’s how much you spend.</title>
      <link>http://talksomecents.com/blog/my-budget-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://talksomecents.com/blog/my-budget-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My budget story actually begins with wealth!  For as long as I can remember, all I wanted to do was work.  I loved the sense of accomplishment it gave me and the joy involved with building up my bank account and savings.  By the time I turned 18, I was a supervisor of a successful framing crew, working on average 55 hours a week.  I bought a brand-new truck and had it paid off in a year.  I fell under the category of what you would term, &amp;ldquo;sitting pretty.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, as the old adage goes, first comes love, then comes marriage, then comes debt?  In our first few years of marriage, we made some poor financial decisions and very quickly ended up living paycheck to paycheck. I can remember one particular time when the mortgage was due and I had to work 62 hours that week just to pay it – with no money left over afterwards. The financial strain became too heavy, and soon we found ourselves taking the frustration out on each other.  It definitely wasn&amp;rsquo;t the &amp;lsquo;Happily Ever After&amp;rsquo; I had imagined for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then one day, I just knew it had to stop; the overdraft notices in the mail, the constant feeling of going backwards in life, and the misery I saw on my wife&amp;rsquo;s face - it all had to stop.  We were more than $350,000 in debt when I finally said, &amp;ldquo;Enough is enough.&amp;rdquo;  I knew the key to crawling out of our debt hole was to stop spending more than I was making.  Seems like that should be common knowledge, right?  You would be surprised!   According to data I read recently in (Forbes.com), 52% of Americans continue to spend more than they make. In fact, for every dollar that the average American earns, he or she spends $1.33! I can’t imagine all of those people feeling as low as I had felt!   Anyone who is ready for a change can follow the same system that helped me all those years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first step was to create a budget.  Please note that I did not say, I WANTED to create a budget, but rather that I HAD to create a budget.  Over the years, you would not believe how many bubbles I have burst by telling people that in order to control their money, they have to control themselves, aka create and stay true to a budget.  This is a huge step in financial freedom, and one I will spend quite a bit on in the future.    Part of creating our budget was to track our monthly expenses.  I soon learned that you cannot even begin to manage money until you know how much you’re spending and where you are spending it.   This involved tracking all our bills and expenditures and carefully recording where our dollars went.    It took several months to get on track with our budget and we failed many times.  I quickly realized that even when we failed, we were spending less than we did before we put ourselves on a budget.  It takes at least 90 days to even get close to making a budget work correctly.  You forget certain expenses and you always try to squeeze too much out of a dollar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of our budgeting days, we fell down and got a lot of bruises. A budget is like riding a bike &amp;ndash; it takes practice. The more you ride the bike the easier it becomes. The longer you live on a budget the easier it will be to maintain.  So many people feel a budget is “too restricting.”  They fear they will have to survive on “bread and water” and give up “having fun” in life.  But that is not true at all.  A budget is just a plan.  It simply puts you in control of your money, rather than having your money control you.  People assume that it takes the excitement out of life, but in essence, it does the opposite by eliminating stress and conflict and allowing spending to be enjoyed guilt-free. You can create a budget that allows you to eat filet mignon every day as long as you plan for it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife and I have been working from a budget for six years now. It only takes me about 10 minutes a month to get our budget set.  I can practically do it blindfolded.  I&amp;rsquo;ve read multiple books and paid for a variety of software and apps to get our budget under control. If you will join me on my journey, I will share my mistakes with you so you don&amp;rsquo;t have to make the same ones. I&amp;rsquo;ll also let you in on the secrets of which software and apps are worth your money.
There is so much freedom in being in control of your money. Once you get the hang of it, you won&amp;rsquo;t have to stress about money ever again.   In just a few years of making the decision to actively organize and manage our finances, my wife and I are down to the last of our debt, which is around $4,000, plus our mortgage.  But the relief from daily stress, the sense of empowerment, and the strong teamwork in our family are worth even more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>